<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Honourable House of Commons, at St. Margarets Westminster, Nov. 7 being the fast-day appointed for the plague of pestilence / by Richard Perrinchief.</title>
            <author>Perrinchief, Richard, 1623?-1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54418</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1606</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18375</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12602817</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12602817</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64198</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54418)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64198)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 771:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Honourable House of Commons, at St. Margarets Westminster, Nov. 7 being the fast-day appointed for the plague of pestilence / by Richard Perrinchief.</title>
                  <author>Perrinchief, Richard, 1623?-1673.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 59 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E.T. for Richard Royston ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Plague --  England --  London --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:64198:1"/>
            <head>Jovis, octavo die Novembris, 1666.</head>
            <opener>ORDERED,</opener>
            <p>
               <hi>THat the Thanks of this Houſe be returned to Doctor</hi> Perrinchief; <hi>and Doctor</hi> Sandcroft, <hi>Dean of St.</hi> Pauls; <hi>for the Sermons by them Preached Yeſterday before this Houſe; and that they be deſired to Print their Sermons: And Mr.</hi> Crouch <hi>is to return the Thanks of the Houſe to Doctor</hi> Perrinchief; <hi>and Sir</hi> John Berkenhead <hi>to Dr.</hi> Sandcroft; <hi>with the deſire of the Houſe to each of them to Print their Sermons.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Will. Goldisbrough,</hi> Cler. Dom. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64198:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the Honourable Houſe OF COMMONS, At St. Margarets Weſtminſter, Nov. 7 Being the Faſt-day appointed for the Plague of Peſtilence.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Perrinchief,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Order of the ſaid Houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. T.</hi> for <hi>Richard Royſton,</hi> Book-ſeller to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty in St. <hi>Bartholomews</hi> Hoſpital, 1666.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:64198:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64198:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Lev. 26.18.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And if you will not yet for all this hearken unto me, then will I puniſh you ſeven times more for your ſins.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough God hath laid Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations enough upon the Souls of men to ſerve him; though there is ſuch an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent wiſdom in his Counſels, ſuch a beauty of Holineſs ſhines in his Law, as are ſufficient to raviſh our <hi>Reaſon</hi> to a compliance: Yet men ſeldom or never are prevailed upon without ſomething that concerns the <hi>Senſe.</hi> For the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man muſt be invited by ſomewhat that will allure the carnal affections, or terrified by what repreſents the loſs of their ſatisfaction. Therefore God was pleaſed ſo far to ſtoop to the infirmities
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64198:3"/>of mankind, that when he gave his <hi>Law,</hi> which in it ſelf is <hi>holy,
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.12.</note> juſt,</hi> and <hi>good,</hi> he added to his Precepts thoſe Promiſes and Threats, which ſhould aſſure the more ſenſual part, that there are all juſt and ſolid comforts in Obedience, and that to Diſobey ſhall be neither ſafe nor plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant. The <hi>Goſpel</hi> alſo, though it be a more plain and open inſtitution for the ſpirits of men, and a direction for the life <hi>to come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 8.</note> yet invites <hi>Godlineſs</hi> with the <hi>promiſes of this life;</hi> and hath the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Indignation,
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.8, 9.</note> and wrath, tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and anguiſh upon every ſoul of man that doth evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>More particularly in this <hi>Chapter</hi> are propoſed thoſe <hi>Bleſſings</hi> which ſhall make the <hi>ſincere in heart</hi> rejoyce, and crown thoſe heads that are wiſe with the fear of God: and then afterwards, from <hi>ver.</hi> 14. to the end of <hi>ver.</hi> 17. he denounces the ſeveral effects of his <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> which ſhall weary and grieve the ungodly, and conſume <hi>the ſinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then, his infinite Wiſdome fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing the <hi>variety of events</hi> which ſhould be from his Judgments, and that though
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64198:3"/>ſome <hi>in their affliction ſhould ſeek God early,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 5 15.</note> yet others <hi>would not regard when his hand was lifted up,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 26.11. Chap. 9.13.</note> nor <hi>turn to him that ſmote them;</hi> doth therefore in this Text declare how diſmall ſhall be the iſſue of ſuch a ſtupidity: <hi>And if ye will not,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>then will I puniſh you ſeven times more for your ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Text conſiſts of 1. A Suppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>And if you will not for all this hearken unto me:</hi> 2. A Conſequence, <hi>Then will I puniſh you ſeven times more for your ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Suppoſition you may obſerve, <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Perſons concerned; <hi>Ye,</hi> who have already been puniſhed, that have had terrours appointed over you, and againſt whom God hath ſet his face. <hi>Secondly,</hi> What is ſuppoſed of theſe Perſons; That <hi>they will not hearken,</hi> not repent, and turn to him in obedience, but continue ſtill in the perverſneſs of their waies. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The aggravation of this perverſneſs; That it was in contempt of all thoſe diſcoveries of God's Wiſdom, Power, and Goodneſs, which he doth manifeſt in his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: <hi>For all this.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:64198:4"/>
            <p>In the Conſequence are, <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Conſequent, Puniſhment; <hi>I will Puniſh. Secondly,</hi> The Neceſſity or Certainty of the Conſequence, <hi>I Will puniſh. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> The Terrour or Meaſure of it; <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven times more. Fourthly,</hi> The Juſtice and Equity of it; <hi>For your ſins.</hi> The conſideration of theſe parts, with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection on them how far they concern us, will be proper to the Occaſion of our preſent meeting.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The Suppoſition, <hi>That a people on whom the Judgments of God have paſſed may yet not hearken to him that ſmote them, nor ſeek the Lord of Hoſts by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</hi> This may well be ſuppoſed, becauſe it is <hi>poſſible.</hi> For all the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of God, how apt ſoever they are in their own nature to affect the ſpirits, and awaken the conſciences of men, yet being intended by God only as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, perſwaſives, and convictions, and not deſigned as inſtruments of violence to force the Soul, leave them ſtill in the natural liberty of their wills. His <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> indeed are as <hi>cords of love,</hi> to elicite and draw forth our affections; to raiſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64198:4"/>longing and panting paſſions for the enjoyment of that fountain from whence flow ſuch pleaſant ſtreams: Yet they are but as <hi>the bands of man,</hi> work in ſuch a manner as is fit for a reaſonable Soul; not leading it in chains, not dragging it as a ſlave. Therefore how much ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they may raviſh a pious man, yet they may be deſpiſed by him who is proud to do wickedly.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe the <hi>Judgments</hi> of God, though they may conſume all thoſe things about us for which we ſin, cut off the darlings of our luſts, and the vile prices of our damnation, ſhew us what bitterneſs is in the end of tranſgreſſion; yet they may leave the <hi>heart</hi> of man <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wounded,</hi> without the leaſt impreſſion of a true and penitent ſorrow. And if the heart of man be yet left free to it ſelf, there may flow from it the iſſues of death, <hi>Evil thoughts, murthers,
<note place="margin">Mat. 15.19.</note> adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, fornications, thefts, falſe-witneſs, and blaſphemies,</hi> and all thoſe other pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions which <hi>defile a man.</hi> So that all the terrours of Judgments, the fall of Heaven, the ſhakings of the Earth, the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64198:5"/>ruines of the diſſolved world, may leave the ſinner where they found him; ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, perchance, and terrified, yet ſtill infamous, with an <hi>inclination</hi> to all his abominations, which waits for the next opportunity of his ſhame.</p>
            <p>But it were well for mankind if this ſuppoſition were grounded only upon a <hi>poſſibility,</hi> that it were only a <hi>ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and never practicable; for we have too many ſad Hiſtories, and too frequent Inſtances of others, beſides our ſelves, whom the Judgments of God have not altered. The Deluge of waters in the time of <hi>Noah</hi> was the moſt univerſal and terrible Judgment that God ever brought upon mankind; yet did it not cleanſe all that out-lived it, and were ſaved from it: for <hi>Cham,</hi> who had been one of the witneſſes how ſoon the glory of this world vaniſhes, how all the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions of bloud and violence were ſwept away by the <hi>opening of the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of Heaven,</hi> how all the frolick joyes at Marrying and giving in Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, all the luſts which by eating and drinking were nouriſhed to a prodigy,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64198:5"/>concluded with ſhrieks and cries at the <hi>breaking up of the great Deep;</hi> he who beheld how fruitleſs and vain were all the labours of men to ſecure themſelves from indignation, and eſcape the wrath of an incenſed God, being forced at laſt to ſubmit to the execution, and end their daies with horrour and lamentation; he who had an experience that there was no ſafety but in <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 7.1.</note> that it alone had made an Ark for a Sanctuary to his Father and his Family: yet even this man entred upon the <hi>new</hi> world with all the ſins of the <hi>old,</hi> and revived thoſe impieties and injuſtices for which God before had cut men off from the face of the earth. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were as it were pulled up by the roots from the Land of their Fathers, carried in chains to <hi>Babylon,</hi> and there made to ſerve ſo heavie a ſervice, as rendred the <hi>Egyptian</hi> bondage inconſiderable,
<note place="margin">Jer. 23.7, 8.</note> and was imbittered with the various reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of their God: Yet this very peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when they were delivered in ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous a manner, that they could ſcarce believe their own happineſs, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64198:6"/>doubted their freedom to be <hi>but a day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dream,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 126.1.</note> and their ſafety too great for a reality; yet ſoon declared by their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, that they had left nothing but their chains at <hi>Babylon,</hi> and came home loaded with their old crimes of Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, Oppreſſion, and Uncleanneſs, for which God before <hi>had made their Land to mourn.</hi> It is needleſs to recite more inſtances; what hath been already done, may be done again. It deferves our conſideration to enquire into thoſe dreadful <hi>cauſes</hi> that bring this <hi>poſſibility</hi> to an <hi>actual exiſtence;</hi> that render in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual to the reforming of our lives the Judgments of God, either as <hi>threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> or <hi>executed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The bare <hi>threatning</hi> of Judgments is one of thoſe methods the Divine wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom thinks fit to uſe to <hi>draw men off from their ſins,</hi> to warn before he ſtrikes, and to brandiſh his Sword over our heads before he wounds them, that if by this means men would be brought to repent of the evil of their doings, he would repent of the evil he had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken againſt them. This was he pleaſed
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64198:6"/>to do in the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> very particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly: He ſent his Servants the Prophets to ſuch and ſuch a <hi>Nation</hi> or <hi>People,</hi> that they ſhould deal clearly, and plainly charge them with their <hi>ſins,</hi> denounce <hi>Judgments</hi> in proportion to them, and in particular determine the limits of the <hi>time</hi> wherein they ſhould come to paſs; as, <hi>within three years,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 16.14. Jon. 3.4.</note> as years of an hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> within <hi>forty daies.</hi> And yet many of theſe were not regarded, ſo that the threatnings being deſpiſed, the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on took place on them.</p>
            <p>In the times of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> though God is not ſo particular, yet is he as <hi>poſitive.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1 13.</note> For the general decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of <hi>his wrath againſt all ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and unrighteouſneſs of men, who hold the truth in unrighteouſneſs,</hi> atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted unto by ſo many ſeveral <hi>inſtances</hi> of ſuch that have faln under this wrath, leave every man to conclude God's an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger againſt his own particular ſins, as certainly as if a Prophet had been ſent on purpoſe unto him. For it is not the <hi>appearance</hi> of a Prophet, nor his particular <hi>application,</hi> that makes the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64198:7"/>threatnings of God <hi>effectual;</hi> becauſe then all would have been prevailed upon to repentance to whom the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets did addreſs themſelves, which it is plain they were not. Or more certain; for no one particular Prophet can poſſibly have ſo many evidences of his being ſent by God: as there are of the whole <hi>Scripture,</hi> of <hi>Jeſus</hi> himſelf, and <hi>all the Prophets</hi> which ſpake by his Spirit. So that whoſoever is not moved at all by theſe <hi>threatnings</hi> of God in his <hi>Word,</hi> though general, the ſame perſon would alſo deſpiſe a Prophet, had he no other buſineſs from Heaven but to forewarn him what ſhould be the iſſue of his ſins.</p>
            <p>Beſides, theſe general denunciations may by prudent obſervation be fixed to particular <hi>Times,</hi> and <hi>Perſons.</hi> Our Saviour told the Jews, it was as poſſible for them <hi>to know the ſigns of the times,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 16.3. Luk. 12.56.</note> that is, <hi>the approach of Judgments,</hi> as to tell what weather the face of the skie will wear-the next day. For there are ſome previous <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances</hi> in the ſtate of affairs, in the lives and converſations of men, by which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64198:7"/>wiſe perſons may gather, Publick <hi>ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities</hi> and <hi>ruines</hi> are hard at hand; ſuch as are, the general <hi>debaucheries</hi> of mens manners, the <hi>impudence</hi> of ſins, <hi>obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie</hi> in the proſecution of our luſts, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt</hi> of the worſhip of God, either <hi>cheriſhing,</hi> or <hi>chaſtiſing</hi> us. By theſe, and the like, the approaches of common diſtreſs, and troubles are as conſpicuous, as a following ſtorm or tempeſt is in the gathering together of the blacker clouds.
<note place="margin">2 Chro. 25.14, 15, 16.</note> When <hi>Amaziah</hi> the King of <hi>Judah</hi> was ſo ſtrangely infatuated as to forſake the God who had given him a wonderful <hi>victory,</hi> and to worſhip thoſe of his defeated enemies, <hi>which could not deliver their own people out of his hand,</hi> and was ſo obſtinate in his follie as to terrifie the <hi>reproving</hi> Prophet; the Prophet concludes from thence that his <hi>deſtruction</hi> was nigh, for it is ſaid, that <hi>he forbare, and ſaid, I know that God hath determined to deſtroy thee, becauſe thou haſt done this, and haſt not hearkened unto my counſel.</hi> Nor are ſuch Concluſions to be drawn from mens practiſes by <hi>Prophets</hi> only: <hi>Macchiavel</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:64198:8"/>(who was conceived to be no great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirer of God's waies of Providence, yet being true to his own obſervations) ſets this down as a rule of <hi>Augurie</hi> of the ſtate of Nations,
<note place="margin">Diſc. l. 1. c. 12. <hi>Niſſuno maggiore inditio ſi puote havere dalla rouina d'una pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincia, che redere di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpregiato il culto divino.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>We cannot have a greater ſign of the ruine of a people than to ſee the Worſhip of God deſpiſed.</hi> Thus many men prudentially comparing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether the <hi>Word</hi> of God with his moſt uſual <hi>Providences,</hi> and applying them to the <hi>times</hi> and <hi>lives</hi> of men, have been able to foreſee and declare thoſe future <hi>events,</hi> which have as certainly <hi>come to paſs</hi> as if a preſent Inſpiration had enabled them to prophecie. So that the <hi>threatnings</hi> of God, how <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> ſoever they are, may yet be brought home to the hearts and conſciences of <hi>particular</hi> perſons, to move them to a ſerious repentance, without the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of <hi>Prodigies,</hi> or ſome porten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous <hi>Signs</hi> from Heaven, which are dark and ambiguous in their event. But if theſe prove ineffectual to this great end, the fault is not to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to any <hi>defect</hi> in the Divine <hi>goodneſs,</hi> as having waved his former
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64198:8"/>methods of long-ſuffering and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and intending to ſurprize us, but to the various and ſtrong <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions</hi> of men, which truly are thoſe hardening cauſes, that make them not hearken unto God. And ſuch are theſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some harden themſelves by <hi>Infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> and that <hi>wiſdom of the World</hi> which is now in Vogue; <hi>Not to believe any thing but what brings a demonſtration to our reaſon, or ſatisfies our ſenſe to an aſſent:</hi> therefore becauſe things fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are not to be demonſtrated, nor can our ſenſes be certain of that which is not yet in being, they feoff at the <hi>Oracles</hi> of God, and make their ſport at the <hi>affirmations</hi> of Heaven. So that it is unlikely they will be forced from the <hi>pleaſure</hi> of their <hi>luſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 19.14.</note> by that which is the <hi>object</hi> of their <hi>ſcorn.</hi> Thus <hi>Lot's Sons-in-Law</hi> diſcrediting the news he brought them, that <hi>the Lord will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy this City,</hi> (for <hi>he ſeemed to them as one that mocked;</hi>) they continued in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and the ſins of it, till fire from Heaven did, too late, convince them of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64198:9"/>the truth of his kind intelligence. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity</hi> hatches our luſts, as <hi>Cockatrice-Eggs,</hi> till they become flying <hi>Serpents.</hi> Look about you, and obſerve how <hi>impudent</hi> they are in their ſins, how <hi>impenitent</hi> in their lives, how <hi>regardleſs</hi> of the publick miſeries, who mock at Religion, and draw matter of rallery from the Scriptures; who ſcoff at <hi>paſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies</hi> as antiquated Stories, tales that never had accompliſhments; and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to impoſe upon the ſecurer world a <hi>diſ-eſteem</hi> of all the <hi>threats</hi> of God, as the <hi>troubleſome dreams</hi> of ſome hungry melancholy Prieſts, who divine for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Theſe ſcoffs you know make up a great part of the vain diſcourſe of many in our Age; whoſe <hi>Infidelity</hi> ariſes not from a want of evidence in the <hi>truths</hi> of God, for there are more <hi>degrees</hi> of <hi>probability</hi> in all his threatnings, than there are of <hi>deſirableneſs</hi> in the things for which they ſin: but becauſe they are ſo far in love with their luſts, that, like <hi>importunate</hi> Adulterers, they quarrel, and duel all thoſe who would perſwade or divorce them from their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64198:9"/>unlawful embraces; ſo that Infidelity, and Luſt, do mutually ſpawn, and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh each the other.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Others are not wrought upon by the <hi>denunciation</hi> of Judgments through a <hi>too fond Credulity, a believing too much.</hi> For howſoever they are perſwaded; that <hi>what God hath ſaid ſhall certainly come to paſs;</hi> yet, cheating themſelves into an Imagination, that they are <hi>his choiſeſt Servants, his deareſt Children,</hi> they are confident he intends nothing but <hi>ſmiles</hi> and <hi>embraces</hi> for them, and that the <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> which he threatens is to fall to the lot of others. And this perſwaſion ariſes from ſome peculiar <hi>opinion,</hi> or <hi>practice</hi> of theirs in Religion, different from the reſt of mankind; on which while they put too high a value, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it commends them ſo to the <hi>Love</hi> of God, that though they do thoſe things for which <hi>the wrath of God comes upon the children of diſobedience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5.6.</note> yet by ſome <hi>vain words</hi> they are cheated to think, that they are <hi>choſen</hi> for his <hi>Jacob,</hi> and ſeparated to be his <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and that <hi>God ſees no Iniquity</hi> in them: and when
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64198:10"/>they believe God ſo kind to them, they will not be leſs kind to themſelves. And it is no wonder if ſuch perſons are not <hi>changed</hi> by the threatnings of God, ſince they preſume there is nothing in them can <hi>provoke</hi> his anger. Thus when the Prophets told the <hi>Jews</hi> of thoſe ſeveral <hi>deſtructions</hi> that ſhould fall upon them, how <hi>Plagues</hi> ſhould conſume them from the earth, and yet a wrath purſue them beyond the Grave, they <hi>truſted in lying words,</hi> they believed without any ground,
<note place="margin">Jer. 7.4.</note> ſaying, <hi>The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>viz.</hi> that the Lord <hi>dwelling</hi> among them as in his <hi>Holy place,</hi> and they being <hi>a people nigh</hi> unto him, none of thoſe things ſhould happen unto them, ſo that inſtead of hearkening to God by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, they more provoked God by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries to thoſe his ſervants.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Some render all the threatnings of God fruitleſs, through their <hi>ſhortneſs of diſcourſe,</hi> whereby they fool them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into a <hi>preſuming</hi> upon his mercy: they <hi>commit</hi> the Attributes of God, and to all declarations of his future
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64198:10"/>juſtice they oppoſe, that <hi>God is Gracious and Merciful, plenteous in Goodneſs, that he is not extreme to mark what is done amiſs,</hi> that ſatisfied with his own Recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude he deſcends not to mark our follies: and, as he is the <hi>moſt perfect</hi> Being, whoſe glory is Goodneſs, that is, an incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible <hi>Inclination to do good to his Creatures;</hi> anger and fury is not his: neither can ſo Gracious a God appoint eternal torments for puniſhments of finite creatures, or temporary tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions: thus they baffle his <hi>Veracity</hi> with his <hi>Clemency.</hi> Or elſe they make his <hi>Long-ſuffering</hi> to wear out the ſenſe of his <hi>Juſtice:</hi> as thoſe Scoffers,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>who walking after their own luſts, ſaid, Where is the promiſe of his Coming? For ſince the Fathers fell aſleep all things continue as they were from the beginning of the Creation.</hi> Such wilful ignorance as this made the unfaithful <hi>Steward</hi> to argue from <hi>his Lord's delaying to come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 12.15.</note> that either he would not call him to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; or that he might have leaſure enough <hi>to beat the men-ſervants, and the maidens, and to eat and drink with the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64198:11"/>drunken.</hi> How far ſuch fooliſh Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions as theſe will prevail to harden mens hearts, the Wiſe-man tells us, Eccl. 8.11. <hi>Becauſe ſentence againſt an evil work is not ſpeedily executed, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the hearts of men are fully ſet in them to do evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the moſt common and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary waies which harden the hearts of men againſt all the ſeverity of Gods <hi>threatnings,</hi> and render <hi>them</hi> as ineffectual to a change of life, as if they were deemed but <hi>cauſeleſs curſes</hi> that never come, as the paſſionate <hi>Rants</hi> of weaker perſons, who would terrifie where they cannot perſwade, and frighten thoſe whom they cannot force. Theſe keep the finner more cloſe to his ſinful enjoyments; ſuggeſt unto him a more than vulgar <hi>wiſdom</hi> not to be ſhaken as a fool with words, and a miſtaken <hi>courage,</hi> which is but obſtinacy; not to be <hi>Hector'd</hi> out of his carnal ſatisfactions. And as the Corruptions of men, or their common Enemy, hath found out theſe arts to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude God's goodneſs and long-ſuffering in the uſe of his <hi>threatnings;</hi> ſo</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:64198:11"/>
            <p n="2">2. There be various cauſes which do hinder the converting effects of his Power, manifeſted in the <hi>execution of Judgments:</hi> ſo that they leave no more impreſſion on the hearts of men, than Arrows do of their paths in the air; their preſence may cauſe ſome diſturbance, but leave no laſting alteration: For</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some men clude the <hi>convictions</hi> which Judgments bring along with them, by a kind of <hi>Scepticiſm; doubting</hi> and <hi>queſtioning</hi> whether <hi>publick calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> and common miſeries, come from God? or whether they be the producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of natural cauſes, which in certain Periods of time have their conjunction? or the event of a fortuitous concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of malignant agents, free from the management of any ſuperiour, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning Cauſe? Thus men affecting a repute of knowledge above the Vulgar, the eſteem of <hi>Speculativi</hi> in ſearching all the reſſorts of nature to trace the effect, and abhorring any reſolutions into Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence as the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> for <hi>ignorance,</hi> and <hi>confeſſion</hi> of it; they firſt <hi>doubt,</hi> and afterwards (their Luſts precipitating
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64198:12"/>the determination, and inclining the ballance where they may have leaſt check,) <hi>deny,</hi> that God was at all concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in our miſeries. And therefore if it were not he that ſmote us, why ſhould we turn unto him? Why ſhould we forſake a beloved ſin, to ſeek a Lord, who doth neither good, nor evil? Whereas God <hi>owns</hi> the works of <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> cauſes, as well as thoſe whoſe <hi>ſpeed</hi> and <hi>greatneſs</hi> diſcover his immediate hand. The Plague of <hi>Locuſts</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to be as much an effect of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation on <hi>Egypt,</hi> as any of the other prodigious Puniſhments; for they deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Moſes</hi> to intercede for their remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val:
<note place="margin">Exod. 10.13, 19.</note> yet it is ſaid, that an <hi>Eaſt wind</hi> brought them, and a <hi>Weſt wind</hi> carried them away. But when God <hi>hides</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf behind a traverſe of immediate In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, and <hi>wraps</hi> up his all-diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing hand in a cloud; when, as the Pſalmiſt ſaith,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 97.2.</note> 
               <hi>Clouds and darkneſs are round about him;</hi> we ſeldom conſider the <hi>Righteouſneſs and Judgment,</hi> which are <hi>the habitation of his Throne.</hi> Thus while God God ſuffered the Devil to rival him
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64198:12"/>in power, ſo that the <hi>Magicians</hi> could vie wonders with the ſervants of the moſt High, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> concluded the Lord's hand was not in the Plagues; he diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited the <hi>Credentials</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> which were his <hi>Miracles,</hi> as the iſſues of ſome common art, and rejected the <hi>Embaſſie;</hi> for it is ſaid,
<note place="margin">Exod. 7.23.</note> 
               <hi>That he turned and went into his houſe, neither did he ſet his heart to this alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Sometimes, though men <hi>acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the evil</hi> which befalls them was the <hi>Lords doing,</hi> and through a cloud of tears behold the brightneſs of Gods power, yet they render Judgments in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual to their amendment, by aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them <hi>as vengeances for other mens ſins,</hi> and <hi>puniſhments</hi> for the <hi>abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of thoſe who differ from them; from whence they conclude, <hi>Repentance</hi> to be the duty of others, and there needs no <hi>change</hi> in themſelves. The ſeveral <hi>parties</hi> of men do in common miſeries, as <hi>routed</hi> Souldiers in a defeat: tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the blame from themſelves, and lay the cauſe of an overthrow upon anothers ſhoulders. How often have ye heard
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64198:13"/>every one of thoſe Judgments which have faln upon this Land, by men of <hi>different</hi> Parties charged upon the ſins of their <hi>contrary</hi> Faction? <hi>This</hi> ſide thinks the <hi>Rebellion</hi> of the other, and the innocent bloud they have ſhed, <hi>did cry</hi> ſo loud for vengeance, that the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty could not reſt till he aroſe to <hi>avenge it on the Inhabitants of the earth. That</hi> ſide imagines, the <hi>Luxury, profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and <hi>impieties</hi> of their Oppoſites to wearie the patience of God, till he take away our comforts, and ſtrip us of all our glories. One <hi>Sect</hi> believes, that all the ſad Providences under which we groan, are but the inſeparable concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of a <hi>war</hi> which God now wages againſt <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> whom they think is to be ſeated among thoſe who are diſſenters from them. The <hi>other</hi> is as firmly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that the <hi>Schiſms, Haereſies, Blaſphemies</hi> of the Holy Spirit; the <hi>neglect of Publick worſhip,</hi> the <hi>malicious,</hi> and <hi>deſigned Diſbedience</hi> to lawful Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs</hi> and <hi>Envy</hi> of their fellow Subjects, which the others are infamous with, have juſtly
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64198:13"/>provoked the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>pure eyes</hi> to make his anger ſmoak againſt ſuch an <hi>infatua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> and <hi>perverſe</hi> Generation as this is. Thus every Party confines Gods love and hatred by their own meaſures, and are ſo far in love with what is theirs, that they think God <hi>doats</hi> upon their <hi>Cauſe</hi> as much as they do themſelves: and therefore ſuppoſe he calls <hi>others</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>return;</hi> their buſineſs is to <hi>ſtand ſtill.</hi> Whereas all and every <hi>Party,</hi> yea, the <hi>beſt</hi> of men, have ſins enough to juſtifie Gods greateſt ſeverity: his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation calls for all our tears, and his Judgments make no difference. In the <hi>Peſtilence</hi> we ſaw the ſame <hi>pit</hi> devour the ſpotted Carkaſſes, that had before ranged themſelves under contrary Perſwaſions; nor was the deſtroying Angel more ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of one Congregation than another. The <hi>late Fire</hi> preyed upon the ſtock and dwellings of the <hi>Orthodox,</hi> and <hi>Fanatick;</hi> and the houſes of <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Meetings,</hi> together with publick <hi>Churches,</hi> were mingled in the aſhes. And ſhould our provoked God give us over into our <hi>Enemies</hi> hands, they would
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64198:14"/>ſpare no <hi>Sect,</hi> that had wherewithall to gratifie their luſt and rage. Therefore in ſuch <hi>Common</hi> Judgments we can never do our duty, till every one be affected as the conſcious <hi>Prophet,</hi> and take up his confeſſion,
<note place="margin">Jon. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>I know that for my ſake this tempeſt,</hi> this miſery, <hi>is come upon you.</hi> And could we be ſo happy to attain to a common repentance, and <hi>walk by the ſame rule</hi> in turning to the Lord, it would remove that other Judgment of our <hi>Diviſions,</hi> which is pregnant with many miſchiefs; for, the Apoſtle aſſures us, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.15. <hi>If in any thing elſe ye be otherwiſe minded, God ſhall reveal this even unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Some men by their very <hi>delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> from a Judgment, through a <hi>prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious folly,</hi> become impenitent after it: accuſtomed dangers harden the eſcaped <hi>fool</hi> oftentimes to a ſtupidity; the <hi>ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> Mariners, that have weathered out ſeveral ſtorms, will ſteal, blaſpheme, and be drunk in the next tempeſt. <hi>Dion Caſſius</hi> tells us, That <hi>Catiline,</hi> being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed for the murders, and rapines com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted on thoſe whom <hi>Sylla</hi> had
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64198:14"/>proſcribed, and eſcaping the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation under which others fell for the ſame crimes,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Dio. Rom. Hiſt. l. 37.</note> 
               <hi>did from this grow much worſe, and by this did at laſt periſh.</hi> So we often ſee him that hath come off ſafe from one Judgment, <hi>careleſs</hi> to avoid another by the amendment of his life; eſpecially if he can any way fancie that he owes his deliverance to ſome <hi>poor Art</hi> of his own: for then he promiſes himſelf, that without the <hi>auſterities</hi> of Repentance, or making himſelf any longer a <hi>burden</hi> to Providence, the ſame Arts, or the like, ſhall be his conſtant refuge. And wicked men are alwaies confident in their own counſels. The Prophet charges the impenitencie of the ſcornful men of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> upon the confidence of their own Arts, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.15. For they ſaid, <hi>We have made a Covenant with Death, and with Hell are we at agreement; when the overflowing ſcourge ſhall paſs through, it ſhall not come nigh us,</hi> &amp;c. Beſides this, the proſpect of ſome <hi>advantages</hi> which a deliverance repreſents, takes off all thoughts of repenting in thoſe that are eſcaped, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64198:15"/>employs them to gather up the <hi>relicks</hi> of anothers ruine, the <hi>ſpoils</hi> of a common <hi>wrack,</hi> to repair the breaches of their own fortunes, or encreaſe their eſtates. So that they conceive a publick Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to loſe its nature as to them, and that it was but a <hi>kindneſs</hi> of heaven to advance their private intereſt; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they interpret thoſe loud <hi>Calls</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance to ſignifie in their ſenſe, <hi>invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> to <hi>eat, drink,</hi> and be <hi>merry,</hi> becauſe they <hi>have more goods laid up for them.</hi> Thus the men of <hi>Samaria turned not to him that ſmote them,</hi> becauſe they ſaw an advantage ariſe from the blow:
<note place="margin">Iſa 9. 10.</note> 
               <hi>For they ſaid in the pride and ſtoutneſs of their hearts, The bricks are faln down, but we will build with hewn ſtone; the Sycomores are cut down, but we will change them into Cedars.</hi> By theſe, and ſeveral ſuch like follies, do many men transform their <hi>deliverance</hi> it ſelf to a greater Judgment, and make the ſaving of ſome temporal concernment, the occaſion of their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ruine.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>Corruptions</hi> and <hi>Luſts</hi> having got ſtrength by <hi>frequent</hi> ſatisfactions,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64198:15"/>and by a conſtant practice arrived to <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits</hi> of ſin, are not to be taken off by common and ordinary means; but are as the <hi>Leproſie,</hi> when got into the <hi>walls,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lev. 14.45.</note> that was not to be removed but by pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down the whole <hi>houſe.</hi> The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of <hi>impoſſibilities</hi> are uſed to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the difficulty of reforming a <hi>cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary</hi> ſinner;
<note place="margin">Jer. 13.23.</note> 
               <hi>Can the Aethiopian change his skin, or the Leopard his ſpots? Then may ye alſo do good that are accuſtomed to do evil.</hi> It is a miracle of Mercy, and an extraordinary triumph of Grace, if ever an <hi>habitual</hi> ſinner be changed or altered. For ſin, by wilful and habitual enterpriſes, having gotten dominion, makes the ſoul of man <hi>naturally uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> of the means of Repentance. The Scripture tells us, what ſtrange mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters men become by <hi>conſtant</hi> practiſes of Iniquity:
<note place="margin">Zech. 7.12.</note> Their <hi>heart</hi> is as <hi>an Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant,</hi> and exceeds the hardneſs of rocks; their <hi>foreheads</hi> are as <hi>braſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 6.28.</note> that cannot bluſh at the reproaches of any wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. The Hiſtorian obſerves,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tac. An.</hi> l. 110.</note> of thoſe that are grown to the height of impiety, <hi>Noviſſima voluptas eſt infamia; Infamy
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64198:16"/>is their laſt pleaſure;</hi> their <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> which is naturally impai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by frequent acts of ſin, is debaſed to the narrowneſs of ſenſe; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to the moſt ſtupid Creatures doth the Holy Ghoſt compare them, as to the <hi>Oxe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 1.3.</note> the <hi>Aſſe,</hi> the <hi>wild-Aſſes Colt,</hi> the <hi>deaf Adder,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 11.12. Pſal. 58.4. Hoſ. 7.11.</note> the <hi>ſilly Dove,</hi> and the <hi>wandring Sheep;</hi> and the advantage lies on the ſide of the <hi>beaſt.</hi> In this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they will blindly charge through a legion of <hi>deſtroying</hi> Angels to come to their ſinful enjoyments, and to attain their wicked hopes. In ſuch perſons, all the gracious methods to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance are diſappointed: For the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet obſerves, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.10. that <hi>Let fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour be ſhewed to the wicked, yet will he not learn righteouſneſs:</hi> So that goodneſs prevails not; nor is wrath more ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, for it is added, <hi>Ver.</hi> 11. <hi>Lord, when thy hand is lifted up, they will not ſee:</hi> All Corrections and Chaſtiſements be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon theſe, are like blows ſpent upon <hi>wilde</hi> beaſts, which do rather more enrage, than tame them.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the dreadful cauſes which
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64198:16"/>make good the <hi>ſuppoſition</hi> in the Text, that bring the poſſibility into an actual being; and therefore require all our <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry</hi> and caution to avoid them, leſt they betray us to the ſadneſs of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitable <hi>conſequence:</hi> Which is next to be conſidered, it being.</p>
            <p>The ſecond part of the Text; <hi>Then will I puniſh you ſeven times more for your ſins.</hi> Wherein the Conſequent, which is <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> and the neceſſity of the Conſequence, <hi>I will puniſh,</hi> do <hi>firſt</hi> require your contemplations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>puniſhment</hi> ſhould follow <hi>ſin,</hi> there ſeems to be a <hi>neceſſity of nature:</hi> For, were ſin rightly conſidered, and did it appear as hateful in our eyes, as it is in the <hi>eyes</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>good</hi> men: we ſhould ſee ſo much miſery in it ſelf, ſeparated from the horrid train of its effects and merits, that we ſhould deem it torment enough to <hi>ſatisfie</hi> any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeful Adverſary without the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>additions of his fierce anger. Men reckon for puniſhments, not only the loſs of <hi>Life,</hi> or <hi>Limb,</hi> or <hi>Eſtate;</hi> but put into the Catalogue, a <hi>forfeiture of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64198:17"/>priviledges,</hi> the <hi>degrading</hi> from <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,</hi> and the <hi>impoſition</hi> of baſe and ſervile <hi>offices.</hi> All this is Sin in it ſelf, for it is a <hi>renouncing</hi> of all our rights to the Divine <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> a <hi>laying aſide</hi> our robes of righteouſnes, a <hi>ſtripping</hi> and making our ſelves naked of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, which is the glory and honour of the Creature, and it is alſo a <hi>drudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and ſervice, of the ſoul to the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal appetite, which was appointed to be her ſlave. This ſeems to be ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted by God, for he is ſaid <hi>to hide his face</hi> from the ſinner; which though it admit many other ſenſes, yet may be alſo true in this, that he doth as a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> who is unwilling to ſee his <hi>child</hi> carried about as a publick ſhame, or behold him panting upon a Wrack. And <hi>pious</hi> men apprehend it no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: for the tranſgreſſion exacts more tears and groans from them, than the terrours of a purſuing anger. There is indeed a <hi>different reſpect</hi> betwixt ſin, and puniſhment as commonly appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, becauſe <hi>that</hi> is our own choice, when <hi>this</hi> is accounted the effect of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64198:17"/>anothers diſpleaſure; yet the event, <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minutio capitis,</hi> a <hi>real loſs,</hi> is the ſame in both: which in one comes forth by way of emanation, in the other waits the formality of a <hi>Judge</hi> and <hi>Sentence.</hi> But this may be thought a notion too nice for our groſſer apprehenſions; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, God's Juſtice is not <hi>ſatisfied</hi> in it, as not fully anſwering his ends in puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing: For it is not enough for the <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection</hi> of the ſinner, who by his ſin being grown more ſenſual, muſt be afflicted there where he is moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted: Nor is it enough for the <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi> of others, who cannot ſurvey and be warned by our ſpiritual loſſes. Therefore he hath eſtabliſhed between them a</p>
            <p n="2">2d. Conſequence, as from <hi>a neceſſary cauſe</hi> to the effect, all the effects of ſin being afflicting and conſuming. <hi>For wickedneſs burneth as the fire,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 9.18.</note> it devours the briars and thorns.</hi> Iniquity <hi>preys</hi> upon the Tranſgreſſour, if it be let alone, till it hath conſumed him. For every ſin doth in its way and meaſure either waſte the <hi>body,</hi> fill it with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64198:18"/>diſeaſes; abate its ſtrength, ſhorten its day, obſtruct its lawful delights, and keep off the ſolid comforts of life: or it impairs the <hi>reaſonable</hi> Faculties, weakens the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> confines it to poor and low cares; limits, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains the <hi>Will,</hi> cloggs it in its brave eſſaies, pinions it as to noble flights: diſcompoſes the <hi>paſſions</hi> with ſad appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, or frolicks of madneſs. Or elſe it plainly waſtes his <hi>Eſtate,</hi> brings the ſinner himſelf from a plentiful Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>to a morſel of bread,</hi> and ſends his Children to <hi>ſeek their meat in deſolate places,</hi> Or elſe it corrupts his <hi>Fame,</hi> makes his Memory an execration, and his Name an aſtoniſhment. Theſe are real puniſhments, which thus afflict the Tranſgreſſour, and raiſe an horrour in thoſe that are about him: God having put a kind of <hi>Nemeſis,</hi> a vindicative Juſtice in the courſe of things, and <hi>chained</hi> Sin and Puniſhment together, as the <hi>Romans</hi> did their Malefactors to the Souldiers that were to be the Keepers or Executioners. But this is not all: for there is a</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:64198:18"/>
            <p n="3">3. Neceſſity of the Conſequence, which is that of <hi>Juſtice</hi> to the <hi>Merit:</hi> From ſin immediately flows <hi>guilt,</hi> which is <hi>an obligation to puniſhment</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable unto it; and the execution of it depends not upon the bare <hi>efficacy</hi> of ſin, but upon the <hi>Rectitude</hi> of ſome Cauſe without, who, as a <hi>Judge</hi> or <hi>Prince,</hi> orders and diſpoſes thoſe things which are apt to afflict or deſtroy the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. So God, the Great Judge, and <hi>King of all the earth,</hi> doth in juſtice pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the Offenders, uſing and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the other Creatures for the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his anger: Sometimes he makes the <hi>Air</hi> upon its wings to convey infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and rottenneſs into our inward parts, as in the Peſtilence; ſometimes he cauſes the <hi>Fire</hi> to kindle upon our houſes, and a <hi>Flame</hi> to waſte our ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten ſtores. Another time he calls the <hi>Beaſts</hi> of the field, to come and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour: Or he alarms the Nations to <hi>war,</hi> bids one people beſiege another; <hi>to ſcoff at Kings and Princes:
<note place="margin">Hab. 1.10.</note> to deride eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtrong Hold,</hi> and take them: Or, he admits the accuſation of the great
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64198:19"/>
               <hi>Adverſary</hi> of mankind, and ſuffers that greedy Executioner to lead the guilty <hi>captive.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.26.</note> Theſe, and ſeveral other waies hath this Great Judge, to trace out ſin with puniſhment; and he uſes each of them in their <hi>ſeaſons,</hi> as his wiſdom thinks fitteſt, to <hi>convince</hi> the wicked, <hi>point</hi> out the fin, and <hi>declare</hi> the Glory of the Judge. His puniſhments are al waies cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain on the impenitent, though it be not certain to us what way he will execute them.</p>
            <p>Therefore thoſe frequent <hi>complaints</hi> and <hi>ſcandals</hi> which men take at <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> as if not careful enough in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving this conſequence betwixt ſin and puniſhment, becauſe they ſometimes ſee <hi>the wicked proſper,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 73.5.</note> (as they imagine) <hi>and to come into no misfortune, nor to be plagued as other men,</hi> are falſe and vain, and ariſe from our own <hi>weakneſs,</hi> and <hi>impatience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For firſt; It is a <hi>vulgar errour,</hi> to think that <hi>there is no puniſhment but what is obvious to our ſenſes,</hi> ſo that unleſs we ſee the ſinner cloathed with ſhame, ruined in his eſtate, or cut off from the face of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:64198:19"/>the earth; men murmur,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.11.</note> and will que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>whether God knows,</hi> and doubt <hi>whether there be knowledge in the Moſt High?</hi> For we do not ſee, or elſe take no notice of, the continual decaies in the <hi>body</hi> of the finner, the daily waſting of his <hi>ſoul,</hi> the declining of his <hi>reaſon</hi> more and more to brutiſhneſs and ſenſuality; we cannot behold the <hi>cares</hi> and <hi>anxieties</hi> that do afflict his <hi>ſpirit,</hi> diſquiet and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually turmoyl his inward man; we ſee not when God gives him over to a <hi>reprobate mind,</hi> and to <hi>vile affections;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.26, 28.</note> when he leaves him in the <hi>hardneſs</hi> of his own heart, by which he doth as it were ſhut him up in priſon till he be brought forth to entertain the World with his publick Execution: and yet theſe are as <hi>real,</hi> yea, more <hi>dreadful</hi> pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, than loſs of Life, and Fortune, and all; though not ſo viſible, yet more <hi>inſupportable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, It is another <hi>Miſtake,</hi> when men think <hi>Outward proſperity to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with God's puniſhments.</hi> For even in the greateſt <hi>wealth,</hi> and the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preameſt <hi>fortune,</hi> all the <hi>vindicative
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:64198:20"/>effects of ſin</hi> may be in their Execution: for, beſides thoſe leſs viſible puniſhments, the very <hi>crimes,</hi> and <hi>luſts</hi> themſelves turn into a <hi>puniſhment;</hi> while they contend one with the other which ſhall have the ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> and every one ſtrives againſt the natural checks of the light of Reaſon, (which often makes them <hi>boggle</hi> and ſtart at the <hi>Commiſſion; varie</hi> and alter the deſigned <hi>times</hi> of execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>neglect</hi> the <hi>preſent,</hi> and torment them with thouſands of fears in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting a <hi>future</hi> opportunity;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pla.</hi> l. 9. de Rep. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>) the mind is ſo torn and diſtracted: that <hi>Plato</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, If their <hi>breaſts</hi> were tranſparent, we ſhould ſee ſuch <hi>laniatus, &amp; ictus,</hi> ſuch <hi>galls</hi> and <hi>gaſhes</hi> upon their <hi>minds,</hi> as rods of iron, and ſcourges of ſteel make upon the mangled bodies of ſome condemned Wretches.
<note place="margin">Tac. An. 6.</note> And <hi>Tacitus</hi> makes <hi>Tiberius</hi> an inſtance of this: who in ſpight of his fortune, his guards, and beaſtly divertiſements at <hi>Capreae;</hi> could not but confeſs in his Letter to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, <hi>Tormenta pectoris, ſuaſque poenas,</hi> &amp;c. the tortures and puniſhments his ſoul endured, to be ſuch as he thought <hi>the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:64198:20"/>Gods could not inflict greater.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dii me deae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que pejus perdunt, quàm perire quotidie ſentio.</note> Thus <hi>Nero</hi> alſo, for all his <hi>fidling, ſinging,</hi> and <hi>rioting</hi> through many the chiefeſt <hi>Cities</hi> of the Empire, had yet the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> of his impieties, to interrupt his pleaſures, which made him tremble in the Temples, as if the <hi>Gods</hi> did appear, like revengeful <hi>Furies,</hi> to his conſcious ſpirit; or,
<note place="margin">Tac. An. 14.</note> 
               <hi>facinorum recordatione nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam timore vacuus, the memory of his crimes appaling him with continual fears.</hi> Theſe, and many other Inſtances, which Hiſtorians have obſerved, ſhew: No <hi>outward</hi> condition <hi>ſecures</hi> the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or <hi>reprieves</hi> him from the deſerved puniſhments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> We might obſerve, that <hi>God traces ſins even with outward puniſhment;</hi> were it not for our own <hi>impatience,</hi> which ariſes rather from a too nice <hi>ſenſe</hi> of the <hi>injuries</hi> we ſuffer, &amp; from an <hi>envie</hi> at <hi>the wickeds proſperity,</hi> than from any neglect that God can be charged with. We would have <hi>fire come down</hi> preſently <hi>from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> a <hi>thunderbolt</hi> immediately hurled, and an <hi>Angel</hi> with all ſpeed diſpatched to remove the loathed <hi>ſinner</hi> from our
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:64198:21"/>troubled <hi>ſight:</hi> and permit not that <hi>lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> and thoſe <hi>ſeaſons</hi> which the Divine <hi>wiſdom</hi> of our Judge thinks fit to chooſe. Whereas if we did in <hi>patience</hi> poſſeſs our ſouls, curb and depreſs their violent and inconſiderate motions; we might perceive, even to a ſatisfaction, how God ſeldom, or never lets an infamous <hi>offender</hi> go off from the <hi>ſtage</hi> of this world, without ſome evident marks of his Indignation; either in his own <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> or thoſe of his <hi>Family.</hi> For ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time God cuts <hi>him</hi> off in ſuch a <hi>way</hi> and <hi>manner;</hi> in ſuch a <hi>time,</hi> and <hi>place;</hi> in his <hi>Arts,</hi> and by his own <hi>wickedneſs,</hi> while he <hi>riots</hi> in his crime, or before he ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the expected <hi>fruit</hi> of his impious deſigns; that men may plainly conclude, that <hi>the Lord's hand</hi> was in his ruine. Or, though the fire of Gods anger burn not clearly out in <hi>his life</hi>-time, or at his <hi>death:</hi> yet it may flame brightly on his <hi>children;</hi> and his poſterity, with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of his <hi>criminal gains,</hi> may have that of his <hi>puniſhments.</hi> And this may be <hi>his puniſhment,</hi> as being within his <hi>proſpect:</hi> for before the darkneſs of death
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:64198:21"/>ſeal up his eyes, he may ſee the train laid that will blow up his <hi>houſe;</hi> the follies, vanities, and luſts of ſome <hi>heir,</hi> or cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>off-ſpring,</hi> that will waſte all he hath gathered, and bury his <hi>name</hi> and memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the ruines of his houſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God ſeems to limit his anger on the <hi>poſterity</hi> of the wicked to <hi>the third or fourth Generation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 20.5.</note> becauſe their miſeries may be within the <hi>fore-ſight</hi> of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and have the ſame men <hi>witneſses</hi> of the <hi>inflictions,</hi> that were of the <hi>offences.</hi> The ſad apprehenſions of which, joyned with the awakened fears of an approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Judgment at the Throne of Chriſt, may make his <hi>end</hi> as comfortleſs as all the fury of men can render the <hi>execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of a Malefactor. And theſe <hi>waies</hi> of Providence juſtifie the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of God in obſerving the conſequence betwixt ſin and puniſhment. Add to this,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The terrour of the Conſequence, <hi>I will puniſh you ſeven times more.</hi> This expreſſion is ſo large, that it <hi>alarms</hi> all our fears, <hi>comprehends</hi> all that we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, and whatſoever an Almighty
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:64198:22"/>wrath can inflict. For God by this doth not bound himſelf to <hi>definite</hi> degrees of puniſhing; becauſe when we by an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate continuance in ſin, in deſpite of all his methods to repentance, have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited all our <hi>rights</hi> to the <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of God, it muſt be only his <hi>pleaſure,</hi> and our <hi>capacity</hi> of ſuffering, that muſt give meaſure to his puniſhment; therefore this <hi>ſeven times more</hi> may ſignifie,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Greater</hi> and <hi>more</hi> puniſhments than thoſe formerly inflicted: for when paſt Judgments have left us <hi>mad</hi> upon our ſins, his <hi>Wiſdom</hi> may bring ſome <hi>new,</hi> fuller of terrour, and more pregnant with deſtruction, to bring us <hi>to our wits again.</hi> Or his <hi>Juſtice</hi> may multiply our Miſeries to a proportion with our Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, which are encreaſed by our <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitableneſs</hi> under foregoing correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Beſides, our <hi>caſe</hi> requires it; for every affliction that hath paſſed over us without any effects to amendment, have made our hearts <hi>harder:</hi> therefore if he intend us any good, he muſt multiply, and agg randize his <hi>Strokes.</hi> So that whereas God before did whip us with
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:64198:22"/>
               <hi>Rods,</hi> now he muſt do it with <hi>Scorpions:</hi> he may adde <hi>fears</hi> within to the <hi>terrours</hi> without; if before, his puniſhments came <hi>ſingly,</hi> now he may amaſs them into <hi>troups,</hi> and <hi>bands;</hi> bring <hi>Deſolation, Poverty, Peſtilence,</hi> a <hi>War</hi> within, and <hi>War</hi> without, all at once.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Puniſhments of another <hi>kind,</hi> and to other <hi>purpoſes:</hi> That whereas at firſt he did <hi>chaſtiſe,</hi> and <hi>correct</hi> to amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; now he may make us an <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> and <hi>Terrour</hi> round about. In his <hi>corrections</hi> he may retain his <hi>love,</hi> his <hi>chaſtiſements</hi> are reconcileable with his <hi>fatherly kindneſs.</hi> But he deals with us as an <hi>Enemy,</hi> brings us <hi>into Judgment with him,</hi> when he pleads with us before men; puts us to an open ſhame, and diſcovers our <hi>nakedneſs</hi> in ſight of all that go by the way; makes us an aſtoniſhment to them that ſee us; ſo that they <hi>wag their heads,</hi> and ſay, <hi>Theſe are the Men that took not God for their guide;</hi> This is the People <hi>that forſook God their Saviour; This is the fooliſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and unwiſe, that did evilly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite the Lord that bought them, and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:64198:23"/>thus ſhall it be done to all them that forget God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Puniſhments to <hi>Exciſion;</hi> his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king both a <hi>full end</hi> of us, and of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing us. When he is weary of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting, and ſhaming us, and weary of <hi>his own repentings,</hi> as he was of thoſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Why ſhould ye be ſtricken any more, ye will revolt more and more?</hi> When he is tired out in his waitings for fruit from barren fouls, then <hi>he cuts them off,</hi> and will not ſuffer them any longer <hi>to cumber the ground;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 13.</note> then he will cut us off from being a people, and <hi>our name ſhall no more be had in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, nor ſhall we be reckoned among the Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Puniſhments to <hi>Vengeance;</hi> when he caſts the ſinners into <hi>Hell,</hi> and there makes their pains and ſorrows as laſting as their ſins would have been, had they continued to Eternitie. This is a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>degree</hi> of puniſhment than the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; for God may cut off many, as to <hi>this life,</hi> for their tranſgreſſions; and yet bound his wrath in the <hi>Grave,</hi> and not purſue them with Puniſhments in the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:64198:23"/>ſtate of the dead. St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, many of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.30.</note> for the unworthy receiving of the <hi>Sacrament, were ſick and weak, and fell aſleep,</hi> that is, <hi>died:</hi> but yet, that is too ſoft an expreſſion to ſignifie their <hi>being damned:</hi> for in the language of Scripture,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 57.1, 1.</note> the <hi>taking away of merciful men, from the evil to come, and the death of thoſe that walk in their uprightneſs,</hi> is called, <hi>their reſt in their beds.</hi> But when men have <hi>oppoſed,</hi> and obſtinately endeavoured to diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point God in his end of Judgments by impenitencie, we may with reaſon think they <hi>ſhall be turned into Hell;</hi> for that is ſtiled, the <hi>Congregation of Giants:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 21.16. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and that you know is the Title of notorious <hi>fighters</hi> againſt God. Thus all theſe Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments are comprehended under that number of <hi>ſeven times more:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore render the Conſequence exceeding terrible. Which yet is but <hi>juſt;</hi> For,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Juſtice</hi> of the Conſequence is in thoſe words which are as a reaſon of the encreaſed puniſhments: <hi>I will pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh you,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For your ſins;</hi> that is, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you have deſerved them.</hi> For the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:64198:24"/>horrour of any puniſhments inflicted by God, argues the Offence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably haynous: there being ſo great an <hi>Equity</hi> in all the Judgments of God, that they never <hi>exceed,</hi> but for the moſt part are <hi>beneath</hi> the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. So that if God ſo ſeverely puniſh our not amending after Judgments, it is becauſe that <hi>Impenitencie</hi> is a moſt horrid <hi>provocation;</hi> and ſuch in truth it is, being a <hi>contempt</hi> and <hi>deſpight</hi> of all his Gracious and Glorious <hi>Attributes.</hi> For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. His <hi>Wiſdom</hi> is ſlighted, and an affront is put upon his infinite Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, which did <hi>invent</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence betwixt Sin and Puniſhment; to <hi>turn</hi> men from the vanity of their waies, that they might be <hi>adviſed</hi> not to doat upon evil, which draws after it ſuch an inſeparable throng of miſeries. But he that hath both <hi>taſted</hi> ſin, and <hi>felt</hi> puniſhment, and yet thinks the <hi>firſt</hi> worthy the hazard of the <hi>latter,</hi> and that one is a cheap purchaſe for the other; <hi>reproaches</hi> the Divine Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of having not ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:64198:24"/>for the attainment of his end.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>goodneſs</hi> of God is turned off with <hi>ſcorn:</hi> for if he hath only afflicted us, ſo that we <hi>live;</hi> it is clear, that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved us for his <hi>ſervice,</hi> and the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces of his love; becauſe, had he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved no more to accept of our wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, he would have ſhut us up in the <hi>pit,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 6.5.</note> where there is no remembrance of him,</hi> and cloſed us in the <hi>grave, where none do give him thanks:</hi> but if he let us <hi>live,</hi> it is clear he intended that <hi>we ſhould praiſe his Name,</hi> and upon that to ſhew us his <hi>Salvation.</hi> But if he that was afflicted, yet not deſtroyed; terrified, yet not broken in pieces; ſhall have <hi>no new ſongs in his mouth,</hi> nor will <hi>order his converſation aright</hi> to pleaſe him who pulled his feet out of the mire, and ſet him upon a rock; ſuch a man doth rude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>ſcorn</hi> the kindneſs by which he was ſaved, and rejects the courtſhip to a more endearing love.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Power</hi> of God is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valued, and his <hi>Omnipotencie</hi> braved. For, he that hath eſcaped one <hi>ſtroke</hi> of God, and yet will not amend upon it, but ſtill
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:64198:25"/>
               <hi>affronts</hi> him to his face, muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded to think; God hath <hi>waſted</hi> all his Thunderbolts, <hi>emptied</hi> his Quiver, and <hi>broke</hi> his Sword in the paſt encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and become like thoſe poor Animals, who loſe their ſting in the firſt wound they give. The routed <hi>Syrians</hi> had not renewed their Invaſion of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 20.23.</note> had they thought the God of <hi>Jacob</hi> could triumph in the <hi>Valleys,</hi> as gloriouſly as upon the <hi>Hills,</hi> and had ſtrength enough for a freſher <hi>victory:</hi> This vile eſteem of God thruſt their infatuated <hi>Prince</hi> upon another overthrow. The ſame thoughts, if not <hi>formally,</hi> yet <hi>virtually,</hi> thoſe men have of God, who having hardly come off from one Judgment, yet do by <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating</hi> their ſins, ſeem to <hi>challenge</hi> him to another. For did we <hi>ſeriouſly think,</hi> that that God, who at firſt did but <hi>light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> afflict, could plague us <hi>ſeven times more;</hi> that he which brought the <hi>Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> upon our nation, could ſpread our own perſons over with Spots and To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens; that he, who by a <hi>Flame</hi> conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med our goods, and houſes, could turn our <hi>bodies</hi> into aſhes, and after that caſt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:64198:25"/>our <hi>ſouls</hi> into Hell-fire; that he, who hath brought our enemies out to the <hi>battel,</hi> could give us up as a <hi>prey</hi> to their <hi>fury;</hi> that he, who hath gathered For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain Nations againſt us, could alſo turn the <hi>ſwords</hi> of every man into the <hi>heart</hi> of his <hi>neighbour,</hi> and appoint each one as a ſlaughter-man of his <hi>brother;</hi> did we but conſider what Judgments can be brought upon us by an Almighty Arm: we ſhould certainly follow the <hi>Counſels</hi> of his firſt <hi>Providences;</hi> be aſhamed that our Father hath <hi>ſpit</hi> in our faces, and not weary him till he <hi>ſmite</hi> them with a <hi>Leproſie,</hi> or make the earth open to <hi>ſwallow</hi> us up. We ſhould <hi>humble</hi> our ſelves more in the appehenſions of what might befal us, than be troubled, or <hi>murmur</hi> for what we already ſuffer, leſt God puniſh us <hi>ſeven times more for our ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Text</hi> being thus conſidered; the <hi>Application</hi> of it will ſhew us what we are to think of our <hi>preſent</hi> and <hi>future condition.</hi> For <hi>Our caſe</hi> is the ſame with theirs in the <hi>Suppoſition:</hi> as if we alſo had been the very People God had in
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:64198:26"/>his proſpect when he ſpake this Text. We of <hi>this Generation</hi> have been <hi>a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of wrath,</hi> and ſeem to have been born to be as <hi>Fewel</hi> for Judgments; or to have been called from the <hi>Womb,</hi> and ſummoned from the <hi>lower parts of the earth,</hi> to come forth and behold <hi>what deſolations God can bring upon a Land, for the wickedneſs of them that dwell therein.</hi> For thoſe plagues and miſeries which did uſe to be <hi>divided</hi> among ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Ages, and to come <hi>ſingly,</hi> and in <hi>certain Periods</hi> of time; have all fallen upon <hi>us,</hi> with as much ſpeed as that of haſtie Meſſengers, one treading upon the heels of another; that we have had ſcarce time to ſurvey the <hi>waſtes</hi> which one hath made, ere another came to call for our <hi>tears</hi> and <hi>wonder.</hi> Let us <hi>ſit down</hi> upon our <hi>Ruines,</hi> and recount them if we can. We have ſeen a tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Civil War,</hi> with all the innumerable Series of its <hi>miſeries,</hi> and of its <hi>ſins,</hi> bringing <hi>Poverty,</hi> and <hi>Deſolation,</hi> upon the far greateſt part of the Kingdom; deſiling moſt men with <hi>innocent bloud,</hi> introducing <hi>Schiſms, Haereſies, Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:64198:26"/>and <hi>Atheiſm;</hi> tempting men to <hi>perjuries,</hi> and the practice of moſt <hi>dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Arts;</hi> which iniquities ought to fill us with more ſorrows, than our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward miſeries did.</p>
            <p>When this was ended by a <hi>Mercy</hi> above our merits, and too great for our hopes, in the reſtoring of our lawful <hi>Prince,</hi> and our ancient <hi>Rights,</hi> and yet neither our late unhappineſſes, nor preſent bleſſings, did prevail to repentance; but God had waited <hi>three years, ſeeking the fruits</hi> of his Providences, <hi>and finding none,</hi> yea, had granted <hi>one year</hi> more to the <hi>interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of his own <hi>Goodneſs;</hi> then came up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us a <hi>Forrain War.</hi> Wherein, though we have hitherto no reaſon to complain of a want of mercy; becauſe he hath crowned our juſt battels with <hi>ſucceſs:</hi> yet ſtill that which <hi>coſts</hi> ſo much Bloud, and Treaſure, muſt be accounted a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; &amp; it is no little miſery to be <hi>neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated</hi> by Arms to maintain our <hi>own rights.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>While we were thus buſied with <hi>cares</hi> againſt men, God ſurpriſes us with new <hi>fears</hi> from himſelf, and brings ſuch a <hi>Plague</hi> upon us, that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:64198:27"/>neither we, nor our Fathers, nor their Fore-fathers, for many Generations, had ever known the like.</p>
            <p>Ere the <hi>deſtroying Angel</hi> had finiſhed his work here, and while he was raging in many other places of the Nation, a <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſs Fire</hi> &amp; <hi>devouring flame,</hi> came upon our chief <hi>City,</hi> the <hi>Queen of our Provinces,</hi> which conſumed the <hi>prices</hi> of many years labours, and thoſe publick <hi>Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> which had out-laſted the injuries of many hundred <hi>Ages,</hi> in the ſpace of far leſs <hi>hours.</hi> The ſad Conſequences of which, are yet not known, as if clouded in its own ſmoake: but we may conceive that as burning <hi>Mountains</hi> ſcatter their aſhes, and ſpread a deſolation and barrenneſs over the neighbouring <hi>Plains</hi> and <hi>Fields;</hi> ſo this burning <hi>City,</hi> may over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread the leſſer Towns and Villages with <hi>want</hi> of <hi>Trade,</hi> and <hi>Poverty;</hi> and caſt forth ſomething of her ruines upon the whole Nation. But, notwithſtanding <hi>this is come upon us,</hi> which I conceive are greater puniſhments than the <hi>Text</hi> ſuppoſes, yet the other part of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is alſo too true of us; For,</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:64198:27"/>
            <p>
               <hi>We have not yet for all this hearkened unto the Lord,</hi> Alas! this is too poor an Expreſſion for us to ſay, <hi>We have not hearkened,</hi> for <hi>we have revolted more and more;</hi> we are ſo far from <hi>forſaking</hi> our ſins, that we have <hi>encreaſed</hi> them; made it our buſineſs to out-vie Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with our Tranſgreſſions; as if Puniſhments were <hi>Inſtructions</hi> to impiety, and it is too evident they have been uſed as <hi>opportunities</hi> for greater Crimes. I am aſhamed to rehearſe them, they are ſo <hi>bruitiſh</hi> and abominable; beſides, their <hi>number</hi> exceeds, as well as their <hi>foulneſs</hi> affrights the memory: and indeed there is no need to repreſent them; for our Iniquities are not only <hi>marked before the Lord,</hi> but they are alſo, as written with a beam of the Sun, ſo plain, that <hi>he who runs may read them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus therefore when our <hi>Caſe</hi> is wholly the ſame with the <hi>Suppoſition,</hi> what remains for us, but a <hi>fearful look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for, and expectation of, God's more fiery Indignation,</hi> that on us alſo the Conſequence ſhould be fulfilled, and that God ſhould <hi>puniſh us ſeven times
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:64198:28"/>more;</hi> that he ſhould bring upon us <hi>greater,</hi> and other <hi>ſorts</hi> of Puniſhments. He hath already puniſhed us to <hi>Correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and we have not amended: Nay, we are not confounded, though he hath puniſhed us to a <hi>terrour</hi> and <hi>example;</hi> for he hath <hi>called Heaven and Earth to witneſs;</hi> he hath cited all the Nations, that know us, in the world, to <hi>Judge betwixt him and us:</hi> for he hath pleaded againſt us in his Judgments, diſcovering our nakedneſs, and putting us to an open ſhame. For all the world knows, that <hi>the righteous Judge will not deal un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly:</hi> and therefore in that he hath brought upon us ſo great <hi>deſtructions,</hi> it is certain we had greater <hi>abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> for where Judgments are engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, on the reverſe Iniquities are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed; there needs no more to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the guilt of <hi>Sodom,</hi> than to tell the <hi>Travellers</hi> as they go along, <hi>There once was a City where there now is a pitchie Lake.</hi> And when the <hi>Marriners</hi> and <hi>Ship-Maſters</hi> ſhall ſaile by our <hi>Shores,</hi> and ſay, <hi>How is the Joyous City become a deſolation?</hi> They will ſoon
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:64198:28"/>ſubjoyn, <hi>How was the faithful City be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an harlot, and unrighteouſneſs lodged in her?</hi> Therefore God hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready puniſhed us to an <hi>Example,</hi> and there remains only now that he ſhould puniſh us to <hi>Exciſion</hi> and <hi>Vengeance,</hi> which himſelf only knows, <hi>how ſoon</hi> may come upon us, and by <hi>what waies</hi> his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom will proceed to execution: we our ſelves may gueſs by our ſins and terrours that it is not far off.</p>
            <p>I tremble to think, that he may make our proud and cruel <hi>Enemies</hi> to land up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Coaſts, who ſhall <hi>ſport</hi> with our bloud, and make our labours the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to their luſts: who may drive us to ſeek the mercy of leſs barbarous <hi>Indians,</hi> and leave the Land of our Fathers to their ſatisfaction. Or, he may cut off <hi>us,</hi> and this good <hi>Land</hi> together, withdraw the Foundation of this (as Hiſtories tells us, he hath done of other) <hi>Iſland,</hi> and let it ſink from the <hi>arms</hi> to the <hi>bottom</hi> of the Sea. Or, he may by ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard-of way, <hi>turn this</hi> whole <hi>Nation into Hell,</hi> that have ſo long forgotten God. Theſe are the horrours of that
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:64198:29"/>Conſequence, which we <hi>deſerve</hi> ſhould ſeize on us; and which <hi>certainly</hi> will, unleſs we labour to prevent them.</p>
            <p>But how can that be? Can it be by a <hi>continuance,</hi> and <hi>encreaſe</hi> of ſin? If ſo, let us go on then, and let us encreaſe our confidence; Let the <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>Impiety</hi> invent ſome <hi>new</hi> ſin that may ſurprize the fore-ſight of Eternity; let them find out ſome <hi>bold,</hi> and <hi>brave</hi> tranſgreſſion that will ſecure men from Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie, and <hi>terrifie</hi> God himſelf from his own wrath. But alas! how can <hi>the pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheards of the earth ſtrive with their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker?</hi> How can the <hi>ſmall duſt of the ballance</hi> contend with him that <hi>ſitteth on the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the heavens? Who ever hardened himſelf againſt the Lord and proſpered?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If then it cannot be done this way, can we do it by <hi>breaking off our ſins</hi> by repentance, and humbling our ſelves before the Smiter? Yes, this will do it: For, the <hi>amendment</hi> of our lives is able to reſcue us from our <hi>preſent</hi> miſeries, and preſerve us from the evil that is yet <hi>to come.</hi> Such a <hi>change</hi> in man works another in God; turns all
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:64198:29"/>his <hi>frowns</hi> into <hi>ſmiles;</hi> makes his <hi>Fury</hi> againſt, to become <hi>Zeal</hi> for, us; alters the <hi>thunder</hi> of his threatnings, to the <hi>ſounding of his bowels;</hi> and his <hi>compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> and <hi>repentings</hi> will be <hi>kindled in him</hi> inſtead of kindling the <hi>fire</hi> of his <hi>Jealouſie;</hi> ſo that this will prevent that Ruine which we ſee gathering about us.</p>
            <p>But then the <hi>difficulty</hi> returns, How ſhall this repentance be wrought, if the Judgments of God will not do it? For, though we may believe, many <hi>private perſons</hi> mourn in ſecret for the ſins, and miſeries of the Nation, yet this is not enough; becauſe, <hi>publick ſins</hi> muſt have a <hi>publick repentance;</hi> beſides, God may take away theſe <hi>merciful men from the evil to come;</hi> and then by whom muſt we look for a common delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance? When there are ſo many <hi>Atheiſts</hi> and <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> ſo many <hi>fools</hi> and half-witted <hi>Scepticks,</hi> ſo many <hi>factious</hi> and <hi>voluptuous</hi> perſons, as make up the greater bulk of this Nation; who all think there is <hi>no need</hi> of repentance, or are reſolved not to do it themſelves: what hopes can we have of a publick
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:64198:30"/>amendment? There remains nothing <hi>viſible</hi> for our comforts but this, The <hi>Example,</hi> and <hi>Induſtry</hi> of thoſe in <hi>Power</hi> to take away all <hi>publick abominations;</hi> this under God is our only ground for hope, and this by his aſſiſtance will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it, (unleſs our <hi>Iniquities come to the full,</hi> ere they apply themſelves to the work:) For <hi>Government</hi> is the ſoul of <hi>Society,</hi> and Magiſtrates in Church and State are as the upper ſoul and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectual</hi> faculties to guide the whole to ſafety, and honour: if theſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be once ſet right in a way that is good, I cannot ſay, They ſhall have <hi>all;</hi> but am ſure, they ſhall have <hi>many followers,</hi> and the tears of repentance will bedew the publick face of the Nation.</p>
            <p>This I humbly conceive to be, in ſome meaſure, the duty of the <hi>Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part</hi> of this <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> who have their ſhare in Government. It lies upon you, within the juſt limits of your power, to do that Right to <hi>God,</hi> to this your <hi>Country,</hi> and to your own <hi>Honour,</hi> which are juſtly expected from you. For, if
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:64198:30"/>the Publick be <hi>guilty,</hi> You cannot be thought <hi>innocent:</hi> if we be <hi>miſerable,</hi> You cannot be <hi>happy.</hi> Let it not be ſaid in following Generations, (if there ſhall be any after this,) <hi>That You ſate in Council, and the whole Nation commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted folly.</hi> Let not <hi>Poſterity</hi> ſay, and future <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> write, <hi>Theſe men were concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Publick Juſtice, and yet Impiety was ſo high, that God brought ſuch and ſuch diſmal Plagues upon the Kingdom.</hi> Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>miſeries</hi> are taken as <hi>reproaches</hi> of thoſe who are in <hi>power</hi> to prevent pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>Sins.</hi> You have exceeded all <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples</hi> in your proviſions for the <hi>Honour</hi> of your King, and our ſafety from a <hi>Forrain</hi> Enemy: Let that move you now to exceed Your ſelves, do ſomething alſo for the honour of <hi>God,</hi> and the advancement of <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi> You have comforted the hearts of the People by your Zeal againſt the <hi>Old Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> of our Faith; let the ſame be exerted againſt <hi>all.</hi> Give ſome <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> to <hi>Religion;</hi> that if wicked men will not <hi>love</hi> it, yet they may not dare
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:64198:31"/>to <hi>deſpiſe</hi> it; that, if their hearts will not <hi>renounce</hi> their luſts, yet let it not be ſafe to <hi>act</hi> them in the face of the Sun. Give ſome <hi>power</hi> and force to <hi>Holineſs;</hi> make ſome brave Attempts, in ſpight of the <hi>Corruptions</hi> of our Age, to reſtore ſomewhat of the <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> that Wickedneſs may be cloathed with ſhame, and be the aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of a City and Nation. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult the <hi>Honour</hi> of your own <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> and let your Lives and Examples be as Sacred as your Laws: that men may <hi>praiſe</hi> them, and not dare to <hi>violate</hi> theſe. If God ſhall be pleaſed by your means to bring this great, yet miſerable, <hi>People,</hi> to repentance; and to ſave them from the <hi>depth</hi> of miſery, on whoſe <hi>brink</hi> both You and We do all now ſtand: How will all Generations <hi>call you bleſſed!</hi> your <hi>Memories</hi> will out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſt Monuments of Braſs and Marble. God will make you <hi>rejoyce with his Inheritance,</hi> and your Seed ſhall poſſeſs the Land, in the fruition of all thoſe comforts wherewith he ſatitates righteous
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:64198:31"/>Hearts, &amp; crowns wiſe Heads; For which, may his infinite mercie fit you and us, through the merits of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To <hi>whom, with the Father, and the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Spirit, be given all obedience, and aſcribed all Honour and Glory both now and for evermore.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
